So, Ajahn, I think about
when I should punish
the mind and when I should simply
not give in to its
demands.  Hmm, because
sometimes it's obvious that
he's telling you to
do it, and there's a lot of
pressure, and you just do
n't do it.  Hmm,
but other times it
feels like there would be
more room for...hmm,
well, it's a lesser demand
that he's making, and it's
more of just a
reaction, and you still
want to send him a
message.  Hmm, so the
practical example
I can give
is something that I think
anyone who's been
in a monastery would
understand.  Hmm, let's say
you're expecting a day off
work and something
happens and you
suddenly feel like
you don't really
like it.  Hmm, if
you're an example of how
to punish the mind, in
which case, if it's
actually acting out and, um,
resisting, that would be like
saying, "
Okay, I see you're
kicking and
screaming right now, so the
next time
we have a day off,
we're going to work anyway,
going to work anyway,
just to send
it this message."
So, is this an acceptable
way to punish
the mind, and how do you
know when to
do it and when to be
a little more passive?
Yes.  Yes, I would say so
.  Yes.  Yes.  I would
say it's because
choices and decisions have to
be, as I say,
informed by a state of
mind, because people
can easily fall into
blind determination.  So
the mind got upset because it
had to work, and
then, well, from now on and
forever, I will always
work so that I do
n't have to
face this
problem again.  In other
words, it is a mistake to
fall into such an
overly determined
level of
dutanga practice because it
simply blinds you
to the point of reference.
This hides her again.
But if it's something
like, "Oh yeah, the mind is
screaming.  I don't act
accordingly.  I
still do the job."
Then the mind
screams again the next
time.  It's like, "Well, how
about we decide, like in
my head,
that we're
going to work now,
even on quiet days
. So you stop
kicking and screaming.
So it's like a decision
made in the
right measure,
aimed at the
right thing. Uh, and
then you're still
watching your mind, you know, "
your mind, you know, "
Oh, now I'm just
going to work and
never think about anything else
." It's like no,
no, the mind is still alive
, and it's going to
complain, and it's like a
level to maintain
determination and those
types of decisions
made at the
right level
that speak directly to the
speak directly to the
mind and not just
come out of some
overzealous... um, let me
um, let me
just get
this straight... uh, they're
the most effective,
like if at
that level you
decide to never
give in to the
central thought again, like
determination, you go
directly to
anagami... at least
if at that level
you  decide and
maintain... I will never have
I will never have
thoughts of
ill will like the
like-minded, but I
will never
engage in it, and then the
whole space between you
and the mind is even
more than delineated
, cleared, separated, and
then what you are
left with is the mind
with its own
thoughts, which
the mind then sees, like, "Oh,
because there is no more
interference from you
through your choices, your
entrapments, your
acceptance and action of
all that blurs the
boundaries, blurs
the picture." So this is the
ignorance that
the Buddha is talking about, the
obscures you, your
own mind and everything in
between, and what that
contributes to. You see,
it kind of reminds me of
, um, when we talk
about not having
abstract thoughts but
thoughts but
keeping concrete
things. It seems like if
you quote the practices of
the dutanga, they are also
concrete and
relate to, well,
that  level. level.
level.
Um, and think about that
now, as an example
that you  brought. So
let's say you decide
because the mind is
always coming up with something, it's something
coming up with something, it's something
like, "Okay, now
we're going to work on quiet
days." And I decided it
for you, like the animal
inside,
and that's it. It doesn't
have to be too
dramatic or
just we're doing it
now. And then the mind
says, "Oh, let's not do
this. Let's do this."
Let's do this."
No, we stick to
it. I'm the one who
decides what we're going
to stick to,
basically because the
mind can act, it can't
act on its
own. So imagine the
same thing, the same
principle applied to applied to
accepting
central thoughts,
where the mind is suggesting to
you to accept these thoughts
, not that they're not there
, because you're not like
they don't come
from you, they
arise, so
even the aran in the suttas
and anagami says that
they purify the thoughts in
their arising,
not that they arise,
so the same
principle that you
decide when the mind
, when you have
these thoughts in this
inner space with  thoughts,
space with  thoughts,
as the sutta says, thoughts
of sensuality, thoughts
of cruelty,
thoughts of evil, I will not
raise them, and that is our
decision here, and then you
know that you go,
walk, talk,
go to the toilet, eat,
sleep, it does not
change, and that is what is
happily practiced in the
practiced in the
sutras above
sensuality. So and you
could see how
people would like it
if you
read about it again, you kind of
wrap your
head around it, and then, but
you cannot, just
on the basis of information,
make this decision
that will remain at
this dry level. There will
not be too
many or too
few. In other words,
you cannot
get the right
melody from the basis of
music just by
reading the newspaper. You
have to keep
playing, tuning the
strings, playing,
tuning the strings, tighter
, looser,
tighter, looser,
until your ear
starts to distinguish the
sound between them, so to
speak. And the more
familiar you are with it, the
more you don't even
bother with the strings. You
immediately  go to
the melody. And that's the
right level
that I keep
talking about, which can
only be revealed if
you can withstand the pressure
to play right
and not play
rough. It will take
some time, depending
on how damaged your
minds are, but eventually,
as I said, these
mental decisions
will become more
obvious, will become
clearer, will not be
something just
abstract, you
will become aware of
your direct
involvement in supporting,
let's say, the choice
to accept the sensory
thoughts when they
arise, it's like, "Oh,
I've accepted this, I'm not acting, I'm not
saying anything, I'm
not doing anything, I'm not
breaking the rules."
But mentally I've
accepted it. I've accepted it.
I feel, "Oh, so what if
I don't
accept this same
mental layer?  ". And this
decision can become
apparent and
made correctly,
this choice, this chetana of
the right kind,
only if you really
purify your
behavior with body and
speech to this level.
Otherwise you
can hear about it.
It may make sense. But
when you do it, it
will be completely
out of tune. It
will not touch the
right note,
because again you are
doing it on the
impure physical
behavior, actions, etc.